Now that you know a simple way to solve the data association
データ関連性の問題を解決する 単純な方法がわかったので
problem, I'll go over the quiz.
クイズの復習をします
And you'll learn about some of the advantages
そして 最近傍法の
and disadvantages of the nearest neighbor technique.
長所と短所 について学びます
We'll come back to this.
ではクイズに戻ります
Nearest neighbor is great, because it's
最近傍法は 優れてします、
easy to understand and implement.
なぜなら、それを理解し実装することが 簡単だからです
Just take the closest measurement.
最も近い測定を 見てください
Here, we are showing the association between the closest
ここに 最も近いライダー測定と 各マップのランドマークの間の
lidar measurement and each map landmark with the red circles.
関係性を赤色の丸で 示しています
However, simple techniques have some disadvantages
でもシンプルな手法は 難しいシナリオに対して
in that they are not as robust to difficult scenarios.
ロバストでないという点で 幾つかデメリットがあります
For instance, a high density of measurements
たとえば 高密度の測定は この手法において非常に誤差が
would make this technique very prone to errors,
多くなります これは
because one map landmark could be really
1 つのマップランドマークが 複数の測定に対して
close to multiple measurements.
非常に近くなり得るためです
It's unclear which feature in this image
この画像のどの特徴が これらのマップランドマークに
corresponds to these map landmarks.
対応するのかが 明確ではありません
In addition, the nearest neighbor algorithm
また 近傍アルゴリズムは とても非効率です
is quite inefficient, because for each landmark
各ランドマーク に対して
you have to search through all of the measurements
すべての測定を検索し 最小距離のものを
to find the one with the minimum distance.
見つけなければ ならないためです
Therefore, the complexity is O of mn,
したがって、計算量は O(mn)となります
where m is the number of map landmarks
m はマップランドマーク の数で
and n is the number of sensors measurements.
n はセンサー測定 の数になります
If there are a lot of sensor measurements, or landmarks,
センサー測定またはランドマークが たくさんある場合
nearest neighbor could become quite slow.
近傍法は非常に遅くなる 可能性があります
Additionally, if a sensor is very noisy,
さらに センサーに非常に
you could easily match a spurious feature,
ノイズが多い場合 実際に実世界の物体に対応しない
one that doesn't actually correspond
誤った特徴を マップランドマークに
to any object in the real world to a map landmark.
対応付けてしまう 可能性があります
The landmark on the right has an incorrect association
右のランドマークには センサーノイズによる
due to sensor noise.
誤った関連性があります
You can tell that this other match is correct,
この他方の相手が 正しいことがわかります
because it matches the geometry of this other landmark match.
理由は この他方のランドマークの相手の ジオメトリと一致するからです
Another disadvantage of nearest neighbor
近傍法の他の短所は 車両の
is that it is not as robust to errors in the vehicle position
ローカライゼーションにおいて 誤差に
estimate.
堅牢ではないことです
If the vehicle position has some errors,
車両の位置に 誤差がいくつかある場合
nearest neighbor will also incur some errors.
近傍法でも いくつか誤差が発生します
Here, the car is shifted to the right.
ここで 車は右に 移動します
So the measurements are also shifted to the right,
そのため この紫色の線で示されるように
as shown with the purple lines.
測定も右に移動します
However, nearest neighbor will not see this pattern,
しかし 近傍法は このパターンを見ずに
and will pick some incorrect correspondences,
黒い丸で囲んだ 間違った対応付けを
which are circled in black.
選びます
Another disadvantage of nearest neighbor
近傍法の さらに別の短所は
is that it does not take uncertainties of the sensor
センサーの 不確実性を
into account.
考慮しないことです
For example, let's say you have a radar sensor that
たとえば 非常に正確な 方位測定を行う
has very precise bearing measurements and not
レーダーセンサーがあり 距離測定はさほど正確
as precise range measurements.
ではないとします
The green ovals here represent the uncertainties
この緑色の 楕円は
in the range and bearing dimensions
これらのレーダー測定の 距離と方位のディメンションの
for these radar measurements.
不確実性を表しています
Nearest neighbor would pick this match,
近傍法は この相手を選びますが
but this other match is more likely
センサーが方位ディメンションにおいて 非常に正確で
given that the sensor is very accurate in the bearing
距離ディメンションにおいて さほど正確でない場合
dimension and not as accurate in the range dimension.
この他方の相手のほうが 適しています
So let's summarize.
ではまとめましょう
The nearest neighbor data association technique
近傍法の データ関連付け手法は
is easy to understand and implement,
理解して実装するのは 簡単で
and it works well in many situations.
多くの状況で うまく機能します
However, it is not as robust to large densities
でも ローカライゼーションにおいて 密度の大きい測定
of measurements, sensor noise, or errors
センサーノイズ または誤差には
in position estimates.
堅牢ではありません
It can be inefficient to compute,
計算するには 非効率なうえ
and also does not take sensor uncertainties into account.
センサーの不確実性も 考慮しません
Now that you know how to associate the sensor
これで 取得した センサー測定値を
measurements you get with landmarks in the map, next
マップのランドマークと 関連付ける方法がわかったので
you'll learn how to implement the update step of the particle
次はパーティクルフィルターの 更新ステップを
filter.
実装する方法を学習します